Hello.
This is J.B.
I'm with Austin Homebrew Supply here in Austin Texas.
Today we are discussing wine equipment; right now I want to talk a little bit about champagne bottles.
Now, champagne bottles are a catch all term for bottles of this kind of nature right here.
Generally thick walled with a little bit of halo of glass right here.
Champagne bottles unlike a traditional wine bottle; champagne bottles are intended to hold pressurized carbonated wine.
Now there are not many wines that are carbonated.
Champagne and also sparkling wines are the only two sparkling wines available on the commercial market or even as a home brewer.
The other thing that you could use this for would be ciders, maybe like a sparkling cider.
If you wanted to you could use the same kind of bottles.
So, with that being said the basic difference between a standard and a champagne bottle is a thick glass, the ability to hold carbonation, also this little halo of glass.
Why does it have that?
It has that so that with a champagne bottle you would use a stopper either a plastic type champagne stopper like this one or an actual champagne cork like these guys here.
Now, champagne corks have their whole another set of circumstances. If you use a champagne cork you have to have a champagne corker.
I unfortunately don't have one in stock right now to show you.
The only one I have is from Italy.
These things are a little bit of a bear to use.
So, be careful if you're going to get into champagne corking.
Most folks will use the little plastic stopper and then you take one of your champagne wires and you put it over the top of it.
That's where this little halo of glass comes in.
The halo of glass allows the bottom of the champagne wire to hold on underneath there so that when fermentation develops that cork won't pop right out of the champagne bottle.
So, so champagne bottles are a great way to store your sparkling either champagne or sparkling homemade wines.